Varun Joshi

varunjoshi@asu.edu +14808421809

OBJECTIVE: Be in a challenging position as a software engineer in the domain of big data, where I can effectively contribute through my industry experience, software development skills and academic knowledge.

SUMMARY: Quick to learn, self-motivated, goal oriented and a team player possessing strong networking skills. Experienced in C, Java, Python and 2.5 years of professional experience in software development.

ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS

■ MS Computer Science, Arizona State University. CGPA – 3.78/4.0

Expected graduation MAY 2016

• B.E. in Information Science, BVBCET, Hubli, Karnataka, India. **CGPA of 8.7**/10.0

Graduated - JUNE 2012

SOFTWARE SKILLS

Programming Languages: C, Java, Python, C++, Android, Javascript.

Databases: Postgresql, MySQL, MongoDB. **Operating Systems**: Ubuntu, MS Windows, Fedora.

Tools and Technologies: Hadoop HDFS, Apache Spark, GIT, Scrapy, Matlab, Maven, Eclipse, SVN, RDF, JSON, XML.

Data Science Experience: Crawling webpages, Parsing, Information Extraction, Data Mining, Machine Learning.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

• Intern at Early Warning Services- Java, Python, Scrapy, Postgresql

(May 2015 - Current)

Designed and developed end-to-end tools to crawl various news articles, websites and extraction of information related to financial crimes using various techniques. Interaction and presenting tools to clients. Involved in business development.

• Research Assistant at CIPS Lab – Java, Eclipse, Postgresql

(March 2015- May 2015)

Developed a tool to crawl webpages and extraction of information using Natural Language Processing techniques.

• PathPartner Technologies Pvt Ltd (Software Engineer)

(July 2012 - June 2014)

<u>Key Contributions</u> - Member of Designing team, Optimization, Meeting observer, Code Reviewer, Discussions with technical experts, Report writing, Technical knowledge sharing, Coding and Debugging.

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

- <u>A comparative study on machine learning algorithms to predict CPU processing load (ASU) Python, SciPy.</u> Implemented different regression algorithms to solve the above said problem statement.
- Probabilistic Approach to Finding Relationships in Interdependent Networks (ASU) Python, MySQL, Matlab.

 Implemented a system to find, relationships between disconnected networks having similar attributes. Scraped the database of DBLP to get the information on research publications and store them in a SQL database using the BeautifulSoup library.
- Geospatial Queries Implementation (ASU) Java, Apache Spark, Hadoop HDFS.

Currently implementing various queries to provide location based information for applications like Yelp, Google Maps.

- **Understanding Social Networks (ASU)** Python, Postgresql.
 - Analysed social network with various network measures by pulling network profiles from vk.com and create a local graph.
- Ontological Semantic Search Engine (BVBCET) JSP, PHP, JDBC, MvSOL, Tomcat Server, RDF.

Performed requirement analysis, designed, implemented and tested a web search engine which understands the semantic relation between the keywords of the search query.

• Research Assistant - Natural Language Parser(BVBCET) - C

Designed, developed and tested a natural spoken language (English) parser. Categorizing words as per their parts of speech and storing them in separate files. With this base, the system would be able to identify whether input text follows the grammar or not.

Relevant courses taken – Statistical Machine Learning, Social Media Mining, Distributed Database Systems, Data Mining and Data Warehousing, Semantic Web Mining, Introduction to Artificial Intelligence, Rich Internet Applications.

AWARDS

Ranked top 500 among 4400 teams in World University Competition in Hackerrank and consistently high ranked in related competitions. Won 1st prize in various inter-college coding competitions (C and C++) under various categories.

Won 1st prize in technical paper presentation at a national technical symposium.

Github: https://github.com/VarunJoshi1990 **Further Details:** https://varunjoshidiary.blogspot.com/p/my-resume.html